so I've been doing this for that two
years would 100 of these gigs this is
about the last one one more and it's
over for me
and I figured that way to write a song
to end it right but then I realized I
don't sing and I can't write music but I
came up with the refrain at least right
and this captures the point if you
understand this refrain you're going to
understand everything I want to say to
you today has four parts first
creativity and innovation all these
builds on the past the past always tries
to control the creativity that builds
upon it's free societies in a way the
future by limiting this power of the
past and ours is less and less of free
society 1774 free culture was born in a
case called Donna's would be Beckett in
the House of Lords in England free
culture was made because copyright was
stopped in 1710 the statute of Anne had
said that copy that should be for a
limited turn just fourteen years but in
the 1740s when Scottish publishers
started reprinting classics you got to
love the Scots the London publishers
said stop they said copyright is forever
Sonny Bono said copyright should be
forever - a day but the London
publishers said copyright is forever
these publishers people who make him
referred to as voyage patentees and
monopolizes in the trade of book selling
men who
not labour in an honest profession
except Tim there she is
in that these publishers demanded a
common law copyright that would be
forever in 1769 in case called Miller V
Taylor they won their claim but just
five years later in balancin Miller was
reversed and for the first time in
history the works of Shakespeare were
freed freed from the control of a
monopoly publishers freed culture was
the result of that case remember they
were Frank I would sing it but you
wouldn't love it too okay that three
culture was keyed to America that was
our birth 1790 we established a regime
that left creativity unregulated now it
was unregulated because copyright law
only covered quote printing copyright
law did not control derivative work and
copyright law granted this protection
for the limited time of 14 years that
was our birth and myth fundamentally in
1790 because of the technology of the
time all things protected with free code
you could take the works of Shakespeare
and read the source that source was the
book you could take the lyric of any
creativity protected by the law and
understand what made it tick studying it
this was the design and the regime and
even in the context of patents there
were transparent technologies you didn't
take you didn't need to take the cotton
gin and read the patent to understand
how it works like you could just take it
apart these were legal protections in a
context where understanding and learning
was still set
we control in this culture was tiny I
was cute control penny okay
and not just then I'd forget the 18th
century the 19th century even at the
birth of the 28th 20th century here's my
fifth example here 1928 my hero
Walt Disney created this extraordinary
work the birth of Mickey Mouse in the
form of Steamboat Willie but what you
probably don't recognize about Steamboat
Willie and his emergence into Mickey
Mouse is that in 1928 Walt Disney quote
to use the language of the Disney
Corporation today stole Willie from
Buster Keaton steamed by Bill it was a
parody a take-off it was a daily upon
steamboat bill steamboat bill was
produced in 1928 no fourteen years just
take it yep mix and burn as he did to
produce the Disney Empire this was his
character Walt's always parroted
feature-length mainstream films to
produce the Disney empire and we see the
product of this this is the Disney
Corporation taking works in the public
domain and not even in the public domain
and turning it into vastly greater new
creativity they took the works of this
guy these guys the Brothers Grimm who
you think are probably great authors on
their lawn they produce these horrible
stories these fairy tales which anybody
should keep their children far from
because there are the utterly bloody and
moralistic stories which are not the
sort of thing that children should see
but then will be told for us by the
Disney Corporation now the Disney
Corporation could do this because that
culture lived in a Commons an
intellectual Commons at cultural Commons
where people could feel
take and build it was a warrior free
jump it is culture that you didn't need
the permission of someone else to take
and build upon that was the character of
creativity at the birth of the last
century it was built on a constitutional
requirement that protection be for
limited times and it was originally
limited 14 years if the author lived 28
then in 1831 it went to 42 event in 1909
and went to 56 and then magically
starting in 1962 look no hands
the term expands 11 times in the last 40
years it has been extended for existing
works not just for New York's they're
going to be created but existing works
the most recent is the Sonny Bono
copyright term extension act those of us
who love it know it as the Mickey Mouse
Protection Act which of course every
time Mickey's about the past in the
public domain popular terms are extended
and the meaning of this pattern is
absolutely clear to those who pay to
produce it the meaning is no one can do
to the Disney Corporation with Walt
Disney addictive the Brothers Grimm that
they we had a culture where people could
take and build upon what went before
that's over there is no such thing as
the public domain and the minds of those
who have produced these eleven
extensions in the last 40 years because
now culture is owned okay sorry remember
the refrain we always build in the past
the past always tries to stop as freedom
of it's about stopping the past but we
have lost that ideal his are different
now from even when Walt produced the
Walt Disney Corporation in this year now
we have a massive system to regulate
creativity a master system of lawyers
regulating creativity as copyright law
has expanded
in unrecognizable forms going from a
regulation of publishing now to a
regulation of copying you know the
things that computers do when you boot
them up going from copies to not just
about copies of the initial work but
even derivative works on top of it going
from 14 years to four new works produced
by a real author there are fewer and
fewer of those people out there life
Plus 70 years
that's the expansion of law but also
there's been an expansion of control
through technology right first of all
this reality of opaque creativity you
know that as proprietary code creativity
where you don't get to see how that
thing works and the law protects that
thing you can't see it's not Shakespeare
that you can study and understand
because the code is by nature open
nature has been reformed in our modern
technology technological era so nature
can be hidden and the law still protects
it and not just through that protection
but through increasing control of uses
of creative work here's my Adobe ebook
reader right some of you seen this
before I'm sure his Middlemarch this is
a work in the public domain
here's that quote permissions the lawyer
had something to do with this that you
can do if there's work in the public
domain like you're allowed to copy ten
selections into that clipboard every ten
days like who got these numbers I don't
know but um you can print ten pages of
this four million page book every 10
days and they allowed feel free to use
the read aloud button to listen to this
book right now Aristotle's politics
another book you know in the public
domain never really protected by
copyright but with this book you can't
copy any text into the selection you
can't print any cases but feel free you
can listen to this book aloud and then
to my great embarrassment here's my
latest book no copying no printing and
don't you dare use the technology to
read my book aloud
and I have a sing button in the next
version of every book later but